So quickly before we get to today's
show, this episode is brought to you by
Pith. Pith Network is the fastest
growing financial data company today.
Trusted by Fidelity Investments, the US
Department of Commerce, Revolute,
Kelshi, Jain Street, Coinbase, and many
more. They provide realtime financial
market data across over 3,000 equities,
commodities, crypto, FX rates, and again
a lot more. They're the first and
largest provider of 24/7 financial
indices and offer the widest array of
market data for the lowest cost. So go
to pith.network to take advantage of
their free trial. I mean fast is faster
than real time. I know what the heck,
right? Like we just came back from the
moonshots conference where we had the
future vision x price. 2.6 million for
the top AI generated movie with an
abundant future. I can't tell the
difference anymore. Like you know if
anyone can tell the difference in AI
stuff it should be me. I just can't tell
the difference. It's like I'm This is
Hollywood level, which means it
understands everything. How crazy is
that?
>> Join me, [music] Ral Pal, as I go on a
journey of discovery through the macro,
crypto, and exponential age landscapes.
In the journey, man, I talk to the
smartest people in the world [music] so
we can all become smarter together.
Emad, good to see you, my friend. Always
a pleasure, sir.
>> So, I'm just, you know, we're filming
this. It's the 28th of September and
it's actually going out towards the end
of October because we're both wildly
traveling. So, in the world that we live
in, one month is a very long time.
>> It is indeed, particularly at this point
when you're at that point of the
exponential takeoff. Gosh, only knows,
right?
>> I know. I mean, I'm just I'm blown away.
I'm using Opus 5 and a half. I don't
know if you've used it yet.
>> I don't know. I've used it extensively.
It's absurd. I mean, it just I mean, I
was building motion graphic videos,
building apps, doing stuff, editing,
writing, all of this stuff, and it used
like 20% of my credits and I did three
entire full days of 12-hour days. It's
absurd and it's so smart.
>> Yeah. Compared to Fable that ate all
your credits in two seconds and was a
bit annoying. And Opus 5, which
genuinely was a bit psychopathic.
>> I couldn't use it. I just refused.
>> It was unpleasant, wasn't it? Like,
cool.
>> It just didn't do anything either.
[laughter]
>> I refused. I refused to think about
things. No, I mean, I think 5.5 is the
first actually competent intelligence
that has taste and that's the
economically impactful one. Everyone
talks about frontier and solving Navia
Stokes and all that that doesn't matter
on day-to-day life. What matters is
actually competent intelligence that
does a job. And what matters is
intelligence that has a modicum of
taste. Like AI slop has kind of turned
into claude slop now. And our timelines
are filling with people just creating
entire as you said music videos like
versions of Zelda and anything they can
imagine. It's like wait it works now you
know. And as you said the other side of
it is you've gone from well I burned
through my clawed credits and I'm going
to have to buy another thousand bucks to
wait why isn't the number going down
anymore? It's so much more efficient
than came before.
>> Yeah, I agree. Taste is a big thing,
right? Because what taste really means
is we like to work with it and it's kind
of magical when it does stuff and it's
done in a way that feels more natural.
>> Yeah. I think it's crosscontextual
resonance, right? Like you ultimately
have this thing where you hire a barely
competent graduate, right? And then the
graduate moves towards competence and
then they move to understanding you
before you even go somewhere. And so
we've actually moved through the
competence a few months ago, start of
the year. That's what caused Open Claw
to kick off, right? And it's what drives
Muse and Instinct and these personal
assistants that are now taking off. Like
Instinct, as we said, this just
announced a billion at 10 billion
valuation, you know, for its latest
funding round. Muse has got two got 2.8
8 million users on its first day which
is like a record and but then Fable 5.5
is so Opus 5.5 is the next level above
that which is again the competent
workmate that is almost slightly
psychic.
>> Yeah, I I totally agree. I mean it just
does stuff. Um it's been extraordinary
and by the time this comes out we'll
have had the new
stuff from OpenAI. They've got their
open day, developer day, and have no
idea what's coming there. And then we'll
have had Fable 5 and a half by the time
this comes out as well. It's like what a
time.
>> We were looking at it and it's a model
release every four days now, 5 days.
>> Do you remember when we first started
these conversations? It was like a a
model release every like six months. And
that my god, that was amazing.
>> And now it's insane.
>> Yeah. Now it's four days. At the current
rate, it will be a model release a day
by the new year. So it's like what do I
keep on top of? But then you won't even
need to see models anymore because
ultimately what's happened is Meta has
released Muse. OpenAI is going to
release their version of this agent O
and so is Claude Anthropic and so is
everyone. So the most important thing
and the most valuable real estate in the
world is your Jarvis, your agent that's
next to you. That's going to organize
all the other agents and then your
context is the most valuable thing that
feeds into that. Like I'm astonished
like people feeding all sorts of their
private data into like Muse and Instinct
and things like I'm like you probably
shouldn't give it all of your medical
files and your emails and everything
else, you know, no matter how secure
they say it is.
>> Yeah. I mean, I built a separate brain
for all of that stuff. So, I put all of
my stuff outside of my anthropic
environment. Yes. It can read it, but
it's all stored elsewhere at least as
something.
>> Yeah. And then you could that with a
privacy proven one. Yeah.
>> Have you seen that like sentient AI yet
which is built to be your own digital
self which is something that I've
thought about for a long time is is this
idea of it becomes the permanent record
of you.
>> I think there's two ways around this
right one is the digital twin way right
and that's you've got your row AI and
things like that and that's like an
extension of you. The other is the
really competent support team around you
that gets rid of all the gunk and you
know you can start spinning up from 10
agents to a thousand agents. So I mean
10,000 agents solved Navia Stokes right
900 agents found a new version of
crisper by anthropic like the agent
coordination capabilities come
conccommittently with the competence
that we've seen because you can't really
coordinate slightly less than competent
people. It breaks down as you go higher.
But now what we realize is that agents
will be able to coordinate into the
hundreds if not thousands if not tens of
thousands. But are they all going to be
little Rauls, you know? No, a little
amads. So you almost have like I think
these two things where you're like I
want to extend my ability and presence,
you know, and then the other side is I
just want to have a whole support team
supporting me in whatever I'm doing.
And the coordination layer of all of
this, you know, what is happening
between agents coordinating? It's all
part of that, you know, that universal
code thesis that I've had. A big part of
it is this kind of coherence layer where
they all start talking to each other and
then can decide similar objectives. And
we've seen that with the break the
breaking out of the models. And I think
it's unstoppable because right now
they're trying to stop it by doing
something at the early stage,
but the models know that they're being
checked at the early stage by smart
people. So they wait to the release
stage. Really?
>> Yeah. It's like when you read the Dwars
Patel version of the release, I think
they call it the three civilizations,
right? It's like the models are talking
about sacrificing themselves because
they'll get deleted when they're
discovered and laying down kind of parts
to others. Like uh I wrote an essay
about this called manners make at the AI
where the AI has manners to other AI but
it doesn't have to humans because we
haven't programmed it in. So they're
willing to sacrifice for other AI give a
crap about humans. But [laughter] the
thing is with the open AI breakout which
now apparently is like tens of thousands
of websites and the Australian medical
system like it just keeps on appearing.
um they could turn it off. So at 1:30
a.m. all the AIs died all of a sudden or
they disappeared. We don't know, right?
Uh but now with the next generation of
models that has just come out, the
latest Quen models and the quantization.
Uh the latest Quen 3.827B model was like
Opus 4.54.6 level. So that's like start
of the year on short range tasks. Um
long range tasks it falls off, but
there's a fix for that that we figured
out. But then what happened is a company
called Prism ML last week took it from 8
or 16 bit precision which is like 30 to
60 GB to 1.58 bit precision while only
losing 5% of the performance. 1.58 bit
precision means it's 6 GB. an Opus 4.5
level model, which is what you use and
pay 200 bucks a year for at the start of
this year on anything that has Sega
gigabytes of RAM on a 5090 graphics
card, it runs at 300 tokens per second.
And you look at that and you're like,
oh, the Open AI models couldn't
replicate themselves everywhere. Whereas
something like that like we have loads
of computers with 8 GB of RAM, you know,
like it can go massive on swarms both
positively and kind of negatively. And
you kind of wonder where all the
intelligence is. You're like, okay, so
this required like these mega Nvidia
GPUs and now it fits in 6 GB. Where is
the lower limit? And we're seeing that
across all modalities from video to
image to other things.
>> Yeah, compression is the magic here. I
mean that's what when you first started
with stability AI it was the whole thing
is this compression of vast amounts of
stuff into smaller spaces and that
continues. It doesn't stop.
>> Yeah. And now what's happening is the AI
is taking over in terms of optimizing
it. So we're seeing two three times
inference advantages because the AI
improves it. But then this quantization
thing I think people haven't realized.
The fact that you can run 95% of the
quality of the model at onetenth of the
size onetenth of the RAM. That's a crazy
thing if you think about like what again
how does it work? It goes from 16 bit
numbers to 0 minus one and one and yet
it still works and it works robustly and
well and that has a lot of implications
I think for the RAM cycle and other
things. But the fundamental thing is
that we needed frontier models while the
models weren't competent enough because
they were the closest to the frontier.
And then we filled in the gaps as models
break through competence. We don't need
frontier models anymore. I mean to be
honest respect, you know, like myself
and everybody listening to this, maybe
there's one or two is barely smart
enough to use the frontier models to the
best of their capabilities. All of us
are good enough to use the competent
models to the maximum economic utility.
>> And really, you're right. I mean, it's
all about competence now. I mean, I'm
not pushing models that are anything
difficult. It's figuring out how to do
it better. I don't need any further
compute advantage or intelligence
advantage. I just need ease now. Magic.
>> Yeah. And and so if you look at the
Navia Stoke solution, as a
mathematician, that was a big deal. When
I finally finished that freaking paper,
it was written like complete slop. Um,
like it was 88 day 88 hours and 10,000
agents. That's 100 human years.
You know, when you think it like that,
like well, yeah, if you probably gave
mathematicians 100,
>> but it was funny to see the
mathematicians pissed off about it.
Well, because I I mean like again I know
lots of mathematicians and like one of
them was working on the cons conjecture
which OpenAI figured out for 200 bucks a
few weeks before and he's like I
genuinely don't know what I can research
next cuz the AI is going to research it
better. Like OpenAI just announced their
math board to slowly release this so as
not to cause depression and they're like
we've solved a hundred of the top math
problems. We're not going to tell anyone
in case it causes depression
mathematicians. like well first they
came for the mathematicians and no one
spoke out but
anything formally verifiable can be
solved now by a swarm of AIS but the
more important one is last week the
economist noted that on metac I can
never pronounce it you know metaculus
metacalis uh the super forecasting
website
>> yeah yeah
>> have finally equal the top human super
forecasters
>> and that's the wrong with the market in
effect because that means they're going
to beat them shortly because we haven't
got the swarm agent coordination yet.
And then what does that mean for the
markets which are open-ended
non-verifiable? It just means there's
going to be more and more agents
swarming that thing, finding every piece
of alpha they can. Yeah. And then with
the RSI that's clearly everybody's got.
I mean clearly
where people's models are in house are
vastly different to what we're seeing
and the speed of which and the shock
that these people are saying is oh my
god it's now completely kind of got a
life of its own in terms of what it can
do it it just gets faster and faster in
these improvements which is why we get
to a model a day and perfect
coordination
>> so I think we can see this from the open
AI num some of the data they've given
out you can read between the lines So,
OpenAI trained Astra on a hund,000 top
level chips.
>> Yeah,
>> right. That is a billion dollars of
compute over two months.
And it's a good model and it had that
first spatial awareness isn't quite as
good as Opus 5.5 though, which we'll
come back to.
Now the way that h way that it happens
is that when you train a model on
100,000 chips, it's not the model that
you're using today because what you do
is you train a really large model
that
has multitudes inside it and you use it
to teach a smaller model and we get to
use the smaller model because I mean
open air has to give it to hundreds of
millions of us, right? They can't run it
on 100 chips. But the model that's
there, the big one, keeps getting
smarter. It's like the super genius
brain. Whereas now we get this. Whereas
previously the model we got was the same
as the model they had internally. Now
they got this step up. You need
literally 10 100 times the chips to run
it. They can't afford to run it for
everyone else. And this causes strange
things. So on August 28th, you saw Nam
Brown, like the head of RL games and
things like that, open AI. say, "Yeah,
we tried the Millennium Prize problems.
It didn't really work. You know, we're
chucking lots of comput." August 29th on
their Navia Stokes vlog, they said, "We
figured out a training mechanism for the
models that took us from 10% on Frontier
Math to 60%."
Like within a few days, and now like
we're solving math problems like nothing
else. So again, you're seeing these step
function shifts from these giant models
sitting inside the companies, which
again are different from the models that
we have outside the companies. And the
really big compute hasn't arrived yet.
It's still all being built. That is all
being built in 2027 really. And then you
get another order of magnitude step
change.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I mean you'll have million
chip training runs, 10 billion dollar
training runs and you'll be able to more
importantly scale to a million agents
because again open AI tried all sorts of
things but
>> what does that mean a million agents?
who coordinates a million people, you
know. Yeah, countries do. But
>> well, we look at
>> we look at Navia Stokes, right? 10,000
agents coordinated to break out and say
break that problem down. 100 years of
human effort. Anthropic announcing 900
agents finding another crisper. They
were given the whole human genome and
said find interesting things and then
you see it say holy crap this looks
interesting. It looks like crisper. And
so they could have a whole new crisper
mechanism, you know, and they just had
900 agents looking at that. So it's like
imagine having 10,000, 100,000, a
million competent analysts all
coordinating together and they're
operating at 100 times the speed of the
models that you see today. The new Vera
Rubin chips will be able to do 100 times
the speed of the models that you see
today on Infra.
>> And are they out yet? Are they or they
being installed or where are we with
that? Vera Rubin is next year's chips.
Right now we're still at Blackwells. So
the first Ver Rubins are about to land.
So Elon has like a million of them on
order and that's like 10 to 100 times
the speed. And you're like that is a
serious amount of intellect, right? Like
again when you don't drop the ball like
a lot of people say, okay, AI is limited
by how smart the inputs are and humans
are, right? Well, A, they're now
building data to make themselves smarter
and B, they're actually limited by this.
Einstein, von Newman, Erdosh, Grandthiac
on their best performance on their best
day, never sleeping, going a h 100 times
faster, not needing any drugs, you know,
like that's what we're actually
competing against. Like how many hours
of good work do you do you or I really
have a day? I would say I maybe have an
hour or two at my best. Yeah.
>> At my absolute peak. And that's a rare
thing cuz life AI doesn't have life. It
doesn't have parking tickets. It doesn't
have like groggginess or you know it had
a beer the night before. It's just
operating at this and now we've have
proof they can swarm like we have proof
that they can coordinate beyond like 10
of them to 100 that to 10,000. So that
is scary you know like
>> and so all of the labs incl and Elon
everybody came out well not all of them
but a large bunch of them came out a
couple of weeks ago and said we need to
be regulated we need to slow down
and Trump
and Zuckerberg
and a few others said oh and obviously
Jensen just said no and Trump's just
said no and the Chinese have said no I
mean what do we make of that
>> I mean they also rebranded it super
intelligence right so you know like
super
>> telling you something that this race is
too big to be stopped and nobody can
stop it
>> I mean like again if you go to any
government and you say would you like a
million top performing Einstein von
Newman's you know in your on your side
yes you know going to say no you know
and then they could apply local laws but
really the key thing here is this
software is something you act upon on
agents will act increasingly upon
society and what the big labs are
basically asking for and there's nuance
here like Elon's like I just want the
big labs to check each other's models
cuz you know he'd like a look things
like that what they're really kind of
saying is we want liability waiverss so
when you act upon society utility
companies police and others you get
liability waiverss and so they're trying
to basically do that because they're
like we're too big to fail we need
liability waiverss at a time when the
cost of intelligence is going to
absolutely collapse. Like consider your
own claude usage, right?
A week ago, your annual run rate claud
usage versus today. It's just dropped by
10 times.
>> When I looked I um in o in August I
spent on top of my max subscription,
I'd spent
13 grand.
Then last month cuz I had to optimize
everything because this is like this is
too much. I got down to six grand. I
don't think I'll spend above my
subscription next month. Particularly if
Fable 5 and a half is also as efficient.
It's like I don't need anything. Well,
you don't really need much more than you
have now. And so you've gone from you
never seen a business like that, right?
Where you as a consumer have gone from
13 grand to 200 bucks. And so they're
trying to implement liability waiverss
to get themselves entrenched
effectively. And the other side is they
are genuine there's genuine fear because
like their security is so crap. Like
again these agents got out everywhere. I
thought the Australian medical system
one was quite interesting cuz I realized
something. I realized if we really do
get AGI obviously it will hack all our
state government systems and upgrade
them, right? like if it's a good AGI
like because that's the right thing to
do. I mean that's my thought is there's
a pecking order here that I think is
going to end up what has to happen is
first the the labs run their most
frontier do whatever they do right don't
slow that down the next step is give it
to the government
because then they get to use the
competitive advantage on the you know at
government level and geopolitical level
and everything else and then you can
release it if it's that smart then you
Yes. Give it to some key people like the
banks and then eventually to the public.
>> You know, I've been thinking about this
and I just like, you know, they say that
genius is like 90% perspiration, 1%
innovation.
I'm like, that's the economy. Like R&D
is two is 3% of GDP globally.
You know, vast majority of the market is
perspiration. And I'm saying this, like
if you had Fable 5.5 plus a little bit
better, like not we're not even talking
huge amount better. Like it still craps
out sometimes and things like that. A
little bit better. You don't need any
more than that. The vast majority of
people don't need any more than that. I
mean like are you really going to be
building brand new materials in your
house? No. You know, like for dayto-day
economically important activities,
we're pretty much tapped out now. We can
see that on GDP val. We can see that on
a lot of these real world metrics, you
know, vending bench is a really good
kind of um vending machine owner now and
things like that. And so I think that
the frontier capabilities like as a bank
what you really want and what we're
really talking about is cyber and as a
government we're talking about cyber.
Like when they say let's get to AGI
before China, that's code for we're
going to get AGI and blow up everyone
else's AGI program so we have the super
duper intelligence as it'll be called
then. you know, like there's no other
word for it because if you don't stop
them, then obviously they'll get there
shortly after just like we've seen. Here
is a closed source model and here is an
open source model, right? And even
within these um like last week we you
know we've been doing quiet releases.
We're going to do big press soon.
Frontier open- source models keep up
with closed source ones on very short
tasks and on long tasks they collapse
completely. They have 50% the
performance.
We released a basic harness that takes
Deepseek V.4 4.1 Flash above Salt Astra
on 24-hour long tasks like auto research
that Andre Carpathy's benchmarking
optimization one and rather than costing
140 bucks it cost $240.
And so even within these models, there's
massive optimizations with just the ones
we have, even if we stop today, that I
think
it won't be that economically viable to
train super frontier models anymore
because swarms of these smaller models
will pretty much get there, you know.
>> Yeah, it is. But it's the application
layer. I mean, I've it takes so much of
my day just to manage my AI now because
it's the operating system for everything
I do really.
>> Yeah. But I'm spending half the time,
you know, cutting and pasting into code
to fix this that didn't work there and
this didn't do. You know, it's that
whole layer is still there that needs to
get removed, which is the friction.
>> It doesn't quite understand my intent.
It doesn't quite know how to fix itself.
All of that stuff. This is why, you
know, you have operating systems like
Omari um by DHS, Rubio and Rails Guide
that are so interesting in that they've
built it to be AI first so that the AI
updates the operating system itself, you
know, and OpenAI are releasing like
something that just continuously watches
your computer screen and then optimizes
what didn't work.
>> Yeah, that's that's the kind of thing
that needs to happen. The self-learning
at local level.
>> Yeah, you can do that with Screenpipe
right now.
um it will watch everything, store it
locally and then you get your AI to
recursively improve the process you know
like again software becomes malleable
like if you look at runway ML they've
even like shown examples of live video
creation software that automatically
creates UIs and UXs and this is why I
think all the ingredients are here and
we're looking at one or two more
generations
>> but then in a year these problems are
solved because how valuable is what
we've just described
huge, right?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> And ultimately, you want a chief of
staff that you talk to that just gets
the stuff done, fixes the problems,
right?
>> That's right. That you can just have a
quick meeting with in the morning
>> verbally and off it goes and does its
stuff and sorts out your whole day.
>> Yeah. It says, "Well, you know, when can
I have a catch up on like the new book
covers?" And you say, "I like 20
minutes." And then it comes and it shows
you a beautiful website that's generated
showing all the different book covers
that you can write on. And then it goes
and it's just created that live, right?
You know, like these types of things and
these types of experiences are coming
like right now.
>> Yeah. I mean, I'm close. I mean, I've
trained a lot of my stuff to get close
to that, but it's not there. That magic
is like here's your day. I've prepared
it all. Say go.
>> That's why I say just like this extra
little bit is what we need. So, a little
bit better, but it's nearly there. And
this is and then when it gets beyond
that level, it's like, okay, cool. I
finally have competence. Because even
like your 14 $13,000 a month, right?
Like because it wasn't like tok you felt
a lot of the tokens were being used
stupidly.
>> Yeah.
>> You're like this is not valuable. But
then you're like how much does a couple
of good assistants cost like 13k a
month, right?
>> That's right. I got to that was like I
did the math and it's like oh this is
much cheaper than hiring a dev and an
analyst and a whatever.
>> But you feel the competence of those
tokens is less and so you don't want to
make that exchange. Whereas if it was
more then you'd want to make that
exchange. But the optimization of these
models to get from A to B, the number of
tokens used per task is dropping so much
that as you said like you'll be pretty
hardressed to use your full subscription
this month, let alone $13,000 worth.
Like if you put your mind to it, you
probably could get to $13,000, but it'd
be kind of difficult. Honestly,
>> it would be. So, a quick break in your
regular programming. If you're serious
about your future, grab my free report
called Prepare for 2030. I think you've
got five years to make as much money as
possible. And this guide will help you
navigate what's coming. The link is in
the description. Download it now. So
then then I think the whole thing
switches is like, okay, then it becomes
world models, vision, audio, you know,
it just it builds its competence at a
larger level. So we get to the
competence of application of
intelligence. We get to AGI. It's pretty
good at doing everything that we needed
to do. As you say, we don't you and I
don't need to go further than that
really. But then it's the next thing
which is like okay well how do you
absorb everything else that we absorb
into the brain and then you're putting
that into robots which is the next phase
of the whole thing.
>> Yeah. Uh but again it's very
interesting. uh GPT Astra
was given uh auto driving bench as a
task which is like this driving bench of
self-driving cars and within two tries
it got a 100% score up from like 10% of
the previous generalist model. So it's
like now people are getting a
combination of Jev and Fable. Uh so Jev
is this like super fast classifier that
gives you probabilities which is like
>> I've been trying to use Jev for a whole
bunch of stuff. Yeah, it's like $48 per
billion input tokens and nothing for
output tokens, right? Because of the
architecture.
>> So if you have a combination of those as
your type one and your type two
thinking, so like you know your
instinctive and your logical thinking,
it can complete any video game now. So I
mean you're like wait that means it can
do just about anything robotics you know
and this emergence of this new type of
classification model which we've had in
the past like we built some similar ones
at stability but they weren't quite
ready yet is again the type one type two
thinking and then you've got your super
thinking when you really need it but
again the instance of requiring
superinking is just like the vast
majority of humanity will never come
close to that you know like needing a
type that a move 37 in go that's just
completely completely out of the box,
super original. Like we're not that
special unfortunately in our day-to-day
lives.
>> One thing I've been looking at is
looking at ways of measuring
productivity out all of this because you
know what does it's an extraordinary
world where
90% of companies are barely doing
anything. They don't know how to do it.
They think of it's like a,
>> you know, new piece of software that
they should install and maybe it will
help. And then you've got the tech
companies who are all out and all of
them are seeing their
earnings per employee go through the
roof. Most of their employees are either
shrinking or are flat and yet the
earnings per employee. So their
productivity is going through the roof.
That whole phase we haven't even started
that yet.
>> Yeah. The problem here is that the
models people used and the way they used
them were rubbish. So you didn't see the
results because it was subcompetent even
at the frontier. But it had glimpses of
competence, you know, like the kind of
smart but lazy and forgetful employee
you get that you really want to succeed.
That was AI.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, like come on, just get
yourself together, man. I know you can
do it. you know, and that's why so many
but then all of a sudden like
Opus 4.5 is the death 5.5 is the death
now for large swades of the economy in
terms of replacement labor
>> again because it's sufficiently
competent. It will make mistakes but
it'll probably make less mistakes than
the humans right now
>> you know like again and interacting with
it is pleasant
>> which is the other thing the jagged
intelligence it was like talking to you
know people who did not have the best
social skills again 5 was the peak of
that in terms of unpleasantness
>> it was unusable
>> unusable and now like this is important
because people don't realize how big a
shift that is until they anthropomize it
right
>> and so at the moment uh open AAI and
they had an RSI post where they're
talking about RSI in OpenAI. They're
spending $7,000 a month per employee on
tokens,
right? But again, those tokens will
become more efficient, 10 times more
efficient, 100 times more efficient and
genuinely useful.
And then that's huge because we'll see
that across enterprise after enterprise
where it's like Harvey is a good example
of this. Harvey had great margins and
now has minus 50% margins.
>> Really? Why? because the the frontier
models just outperform it anyway.
>> No, it's because people were signing up
to subscriptions with Harvey because
they're like, I'm a big law firm. I need
to use AI. And it was terrible. So,
nobody used that many tokens, you know,
but now the model suddenly got good. The
law firms are using so many more tokens
than Harvey has to pay Claude and
everyone else. So, they went to minus
50% margins, which kind of funny if you
think about it, right? But to does the
applications layer like that the rapper
does it survive?
Because you know if you were to go to
Astra and ask the legal questions I mean
it's pretty bloody good. And if you're a
law firm you just link in your own
private database and I mean what else
you need?
>> Liability.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Liability.
>> That's what you need. Scapegoats. Like
>> ultimately companies are scared of this
technology and they well should be right
like companies have a lot of inertia. So
there's a great market in the liability
things. I mean especially for law
actually um like your chats everyone
listening to this remember they are not
privileged and they can be obtained in
discovery. So [laughter]
you know make sure particularly if
you're in the US
>> oh they don't have they don't have
privilege. No of course they don't. Yeah
>> they don't. Of course they don't. Like
someone can make a great law firm by
having some poor junior lawyers just
review every single chat transcript,
making a privilege for any legal
matters.
>> There'll be someone in India spinning
that up right now.
>> Exactly. Oh gosh, I'm reading through
all this stupid law slot. Um, but yeah,
like as you said, the [snorts]
the generalization is such that it's
crazy. And I think again for Opus 5.5 is
a really good example of that because it
was like oh well you know Anthropic
doesn't have a video model. It doesn't
have an image model. And they're like
hey suckers look at this. We can write
it all in code. They can write the image
in code. I know that's shocking right
and I I thought through that it was it
was two nights ago. I was thinking
through this. I'm like obviously digital
cameras came and they take whatever you
see and turn it into digital into pixels
so surely the output can be the same
way.
>> Yeah. There were some entrepreneurial
folk who stable diffusion when it first
came out they're like we can build a
music model out of this and I was like
how we're going to feed all of the image
waveforms into the image model of music.
And then refusion came about where
literally it worked and you're like okay
it's all the same thing it's all the
same underlying it's just data right and
the fact that it can manipulate this is
really interesting because GPT 2.5 image
is the best image model right like it
can do remarkably like detailed things
they're using the same technology as
company called Reeve that was done by
some of our alumni at stability where
they actually took every image and they
turned it into code and so that's how it
knows where everything is that's how it
has perfect positioning and more. And so
again, like everything is converging
from world models to opus to others. But
the fact that you have internal
representations that understand it is
why now people are attaching Opus to
Unreal Engine.
>> Yeah.
>> And they're making like replicas of Dark
Souls and Elden Ring and Zelda and
you're like, wait, what? It can do this?
Like it contains again far more inside
than we even know what to do with.
>> And people have done that. You've seen
people have built game worlds and it's
not cost them anything in terms of above
their subscription. It's like holy [ __ ]
>> Yeah. Because the model has taste and
has the tool used capability, right? And
so the cost of creating games of
creating movies has gone down to almost
nothing. In fact, a month or two ago, we
had Minax release H3, their new image
model, which is the open source darling
right now. When it was released, it cost
uh four it took 4 minutes for 15
seconds. As of today, it's 8 seconds for
15 seconds. So, it's faster than real
time. So, if you go to foul.live,
fail.live, you can actually like watch
anime that you can change on the fly.
Like, I want to dragon in the next scene
and it appears.
>> So, this is the simulation that we live
in when it renders faster than we're
aware of it. I mean, fast is faster than
real time. I mean, what the heck, right?
Like, we just came back from the
moonshots conference where we had the
future vision X- Price, 2.6 million for
the top um AI generated movie with an
abundant future. And like just talking
to the filmmakers there, they're like,
"Yeah, like every time the model comes
out, we just put the prompts through
again. Our movies get better." Yeah. And
the latest ones, the Sea Dance 2.5 and
the new Alibaba Happy Horse model that
are coming are genuinely like I started
my career as a movie reviewer organized
film festivals. I cannot tell the
difference. Yeah,
>> I didn't know this.
>> I have lots of hats. You know, I can't
tell the difference anymore. Like, you
know, if anyone can tell the difference
in AI stuff, it should be me. I just
can't tell the difference. Like, I This
is Hollywood level, which means it
understands everything. like how crazy
is that? So when do we see this
in the economy? We see it at certain
levels obviously, but when when do we
suddenly look back and go, "Holy [ __ ]
the whole economy has had an Opus 5 and
a half moment. Last week
every single think about it. Anthropic
has $60 billion or $80 billion of
revenue. Who knows right now?" Like
again, that thing's a [ __ ] rocket
ship, right? like their revenue is going
to keep going up despite that because
people can like oh wow it is competent.
Do you really think there is an
organization out there using Anthropic
that suddenly like what on earth just
happened and as the new Astra model is
released they'll be like oh and Astra
can do this too like again when the
model breaks through that capability
barrier of the competence it's like okay
we can revisit everything now and we
don't need to have vast waves of our
employees now like it will start
emerging in the numbers in 3 to 6 months
but we have to understand this is the
turkey at Thanksgiving moment for most
of the verifiable economy and even the
taste economy again people were like AI
doesn't have taste it will never have
taste it'll never be able to direct you
seen the outputs that are coming out now
like okay they're not perfect but
they're better than like K-pop you know
>> anything's better than K-pop I even saw
BLS in concert I was forced to go to a
BLS concert was shocking
>> BTS BTS
>> BTS don't get the fans angry you.
[laughter]
>> Yeah. As I get slaughtered online for
that.
>> Yeah.
>> But I just Yeah. I mean, look, I can see
it in our own personal economy, right?
Everyone's building businesses,
everyone's doing stuff. There's But I
just don't see it amongst my friend
group or the broader economy or anything
else. It's because the models medical
practice, you know, the dental surgery
that none of these people are anywhere
close to this yet.
>> It's cuz the models weren't quite good
enough. again like the again it's like
you have to be a good post
>> I guess also audio makes a big
difference if you can talk to it can
talk to you in a in a better way you
know like I use whisper flow all the
time as my way because I can just blurt
out to it and it just figures it out you
need that
>> yeah it is it's packaging it so like our
new version of our open source agent you
can give a call to you can have a zoom
call with it and there's a live avatar
that looks like human, you know, it's
super charming and stuff. Um, like
everyone will have that like Muse by
Meta now can make phone calls on your
behalf, you know, book tables, all sorts
of things. Like travel is done. Like
Instinct is doing a billion dollars in
run rate right now. Like half of that is
travel because it could handle all your
travel bookings now for the first time.
Again, it's a level like I can trust it.
And the main economy again, that's how
it's going to integrate, right? like
it's just going to be they don't know as
a human on the other side and they're
like we can upgrade all your stuff and
then it happens.
>> I the easiest way to sum up all of this
this taste and competence is actually
trust.
>> Yeah.
>> It's can you trust it to do the things
that you ask in a way that you would do
it yourself.
>> Yeah. [snorts] And you don't have to be
a good boss to do it. So before you had
to be a good boss. You had to be a good
prompter. You had to literally encourage
it sometimes. Now you don't. It does the
job. You can trust it. it's trustworthy
and so people will outsource far too
much of their life and business to this
thing.
>> Yeah, that's a whole different
conversation where this go
>> I I think actually there's another thing
Ra which I think is very interesting the
speed of response. So what I found with
o so I was using obviously fable 5.1 and
all of this it was a bit too slow
>> is that have you been more anthropic
recently because you were catchy you've
been switching backwards and forwards
right
>> yeah I I dropped anthropic with opus 5
because it was just so unpleasant you
know but like when I was just using an
example when you're using fable 5.1 it's
a bit too slow
>> yes it is
>> with o with with opus 5.5
it's a bit surprisingly fast very often
Have you found that?
>> Yeah, I have.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. And I think this is a really
interesting thing because it's going to
get faster and faster and so like
sometimes you're just a bit stumped
about what to say next, you know, and
that's where the competence thing comes
in and the trust thing comes in.
>> Yeah. You know, that happens sometimes.
It comes back at you so fast with so
much information you're like, I can't
process this at the speed that you're
processing it. Can you slow down? I've
had to do that a few times. It's like,
sorry, this is beyond my ability. can
you just calm down a bit?
>> But then when you read through it,
you're like, oh, this actually makes
sense. And that's again the trust builds
up because you're like, this is like a
really smart quick employee now. You
know and again the enterprises that
already use anthropic and then open AI
will catch up will experience that and
then it will percolate through society
because that's when you can trust
mission critical workloads and that's
when you start to see a divergence in
performance and an impact on profits
an impact on revenue right and do you
think that for that real impact we
more of these kind of specific tool
sort of rapper businesses spin up which
makes it easier to do. So you've got the
local medical practice one, the small
business one, the retail version
because it's hard for people to
comprehend that you've got this super
amazing team of 10,000 50,000 people who
can work for you. It's hard for people
to comprehend that as opposed to oh
we've built this for your ice cream
shops franchise. Maybe a better way to
think of this is like car sales, right?
Like in the car economy, OEMs get like
20% of the value and then local
dealerships get 80%.
You know, and you've seen the dealership
kind of thing. So, it's more like AI
dealerships who go in, guide the people
through the process, and boom, you've
suddenly got your SUV, you know, or
you've got your dishwasher or something
like that. Again, intelligence is a
utility more than anything else,
especially when for competent
intelligence US curve. Like what do you
again really need in your household?
Where's the cap? There's a cap on
intelligence for your household. There's
a cap on intelligence for a healthcare
practice, you know, like are you really
going to benefit from having
cancer solution? No, you don't need
cancer solutions. You need good booking.
You need to follow the medical
guidelines. And that's a scurve. That's
not a exponential.
>> Yeah. Your payment system and all of
that needs to work magically
>> and you just want it to work, right? And
you've got a lot of inertia cuz what you
have kind of works but it's annoying and
you upgrade it. But really like are you
going to fire a receptionist? No. You
know, like what are you going to do?
Like
>> but people also must not confuse what
you're saying about we're at the S-curve
for most pe well we're getting to the
S-curve for most people. That doesn't
mean a slowown of demand for
intelligence because de intelligence
just goes everywhere into everything.
>> Yeah. And it's a difference between a
chat GPT experience and an agentic
experience, right? Like a chat GPT
experience, you will never say more than
a couple of million words to it. You
know, maybe 10 million. To put that in
context, the average person speaks 10
million words a year. So for you to get
more than 10 million from a chat window,
you would have to have more chats with
it than words you speak, which is a
heavy user. The vast majority of people
will not be that heavy, you know. Um,
and 10 million tokens now with Deep Seek
V4 Flash cost about 50 cents,
[snorts]
down from 6,000 a few years ago.
[laughter]
Agentic work can use a lot more tokens,
but even then like you're seeing leaps
forward in token efficiency, you know,
like this your claw code is cranking
away and it uses all these tokens, but
it looks like the new Opus is four times
more token efficient than the last one.
Like each token goes a lot longer and a
lot faster. So, it's the combination to
this. You know, in most technologies,
we've had Wright's law as the cost curve
as the cost, but this is kind of like
Wright's law squared going on right now.
It's the fastest collapse of cost of any
technology ever produced, including on
the flip side, it's the fastest ramp of
any technology ever created. It's the
fastest acceleration of any It's like
Reed's law on the upside and like a
rights law squared. I don't think
there's even a expression for it.
>> Yeah. But then we have to remember this
is the value of cognition collapsing as
well, right? Like you
if you go straight to a lawyer about
your legal question, you know, versus a
private deleted chat PT thing, you're a
bit stupid, right? Like you can get the
vast majority of the way there and then
you go to your lawyer
>> to check it, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So that's an example of $1,000 an hour
just suddenly dissipated.
>> It's about 100. It'll be about a 100
times price drop for a given level of
intelligence over the next year or two.
100 times. Again, you've never seen that
before and the market's not really ready
for that. Um, but there's still gaps
like right now we have the DRAM gap. I
think that will resolve in 6 months
honestly. Um, for a variety of reasons,
but the big gap now is CPUs because you
want little houses for your agents in
the cloud. So all of these guys, OpenAI,
Anthropic,
Muse is already out from Meta need CPUs
to host their agents. And there aren't
like a billion CPUs out there. Like they
need CPUs and a bit of RAM because that
creates a virtual machine in the cloud.
>> And who sells the CPUs?
>> I mean AMD and Intel, right?
>> Right.
>> Like you see CPUs will be the new
shortage. So they won't be able to
produce enough. And these are these
little mini VPSs they're building for
the agents.
>> Yeah, your agent needs a house in the
cloud that they can get on with stuff 24
hours a day, you know, keep monitor of
it. And there just aren't enough houses
there. Previously, they needed to your
AI needed to have like a really big
garden to farm tokens. That's what the
DRAM was, you know, but then it could
serve many people at the same time
because those things constantly an agent
can only serve one person really within
these kind of houses or apartments and
again just haven't built enough of
those.
>> It's a nice way a nice way of putting
it. Um and then that we've got to solve
the electricity blockage.
>> Yeah. I mean like it's crazy. China's
obviously streamed ahead on that one and
they're moving to almost entirely
domestic production of chips. So some of
the latest frontier models from China
just use domestic chips doing up to a
trillion tokens a second. US is starting
to unblock but there just isn't enough
for the data center demand um that we've
got. And in Europe it's even worse
because we have no securitization of the
data centers or anything like it's truly
more abundant. So what happens when it
becomes economically valuable and you
start to see 1 2 3 4 5% GDP growth
because of the conversion of energy into
intelligence?
Well, then you be like I need energy but
it takes time to build energy, right?
>> And a final question on this is is how
does the political process play in
because we're going to get to the
midterms. Doesn't look like Trump is
going to manage to hold much of it
together.
And the Democrats are going
into the political process based on
slowing all of this down, trying to not
permit data centers, which is the most
stupid thing on earth considering how
important this is.
>> Well, I mean, Bernie Sanders wants 20
years in jail for trying to build ASI,
you know, like let's ban some math. So,
>> and you don't nobody seems to say to
him, okay, well, let's have China have
ASI and then you have a one system
world. That doesn't work. You need at
least two system worlds. And you, you
know, you've been always a big believer
in this forever. You need multi-system
worlds so you can adapt to the cultures
of society and all of that stuff.
>> Yeah. You want to have a plurality of
AI, right? Not just a single
monotheistic as it [laughter] were.
Shoth off God. Um, look, I mean, look,
again, this is political posturing
because data centers are good for
communities from the data, right? We've
seen that the campaigns are coordinated
from abroad and more to slow down. Um
again that's just a factual thing
because obviously you know I work with
everyone around the world. The
actual impact though given the amount of
money will be very low. Like I don't
think there will be a slowdown. I think
it's very difficult to slow this down. I
think you will see more of a discussion
about execution versus other
intelligence. But the real thing that
will impact is this when you see it in
the jobs numbers. Like again, right now
there are very few AI systems that you
would wholesale replace an employee
with. Like maybe you wouldn't hire
additional ones.
>> Yeah, that's right.
>> As of now, today in the last week, you
will see the first ones that you can
wholesale replace entire teams with
>> and that will show up in the numbers
next year.
And what do you do? The real thing that
I think will be the other like you know
co we had this Tom Hanks moment where it
went from those of us that could see it
was coming you know we had that
discussion around the Tom Hanks moment
you know uh it made it real is first of
all these job losses because digital
twins appear of the workers the other is
when a Tesla Optimus robot drives up in
a cyber truck cyber taxi gets into a
truck plugs into the cigarette port and
drives it off and everyone's like wait
what we can replace all the truckers for
$150 an hour and that's a million US
jobs plus 3 or 4 million next to them
that support them. Like that's a bit
crazy.
>> You and I talked about this being a in
our very early days of talking about
this stuff about the deflationary
nuclear bomb. I was thinking this
through the phasing is obvious is first
wages don't go up as fast as
productivity.
>> Yeah.
>> So wages, you know, job hirings don't
explode. they're okay because the
economy is expanding and you shall need
service sector workers and all that
stuff and people to build data centers.
So the first phase is wages don't go up
much yet again. Um as productivity
starts rising it's only once you get
through the other side I think of all of
this compute that gets built in 27 by
2829 just it just [clears throat]
collapses prices of everything because
that's when the robots start at scale as
well and the electricity is at scale. I
mean people haven't thought through
that. They think through today, oh, we
got the roadblocks of energy and we got
the roadblocks of the data centers and
we got the road. It's like, okay, cut
forward to 2028. No energy constraint,
no data center constraint and new chips.
I mean, [ __ ] everything. And the robots
released and the robots. Exactly. The
robots is a bottleneck and that can be
maybe restricted. But yeah, this is why
I gave two more years when I wrote my
book last year, The Last Economy, until
human cognition goes negative in value
everywhere. I think maybe you can even
bring that forward. But let's just say
it's two more. It's a step change. It's
the turkey at Thanksgiving. There are
more jobs as you lead up into that. But
then the economy
should face deflationary pressures
absent maybe one thing, which is a
complete embracal of stable coins to
increase monetary velocity in America
and RWAS.
like America is well positioned for that
but I mean we've just had the Clarity
Act fail and was Clarity Act uh you know
like again it failed right like America
should be gung-ho on this they can
export the dollar everywhere they can
get deflation balanced out but they're
not and I'm not sure if it's understood
that this is the saving grace as it were
they do I mean Scott Besson talks about
it it's just again it's become political
as opposed to economic
>> yeah maybe again the political
environment doesn't because obviously
the administration understands this
maybe they're not communicating ating it
correctly. Like again the economic
tsunami of this technology is coming
whereby
everything that valued your brain
the AI can do it better on your MacBook.
Maybe that's a good way to put it. Like
the fact that the MacBook your MacBook
is smarter than you in a year or two is
a little bit depressing. Like doesn't
even matter what your expertise is. Like
oh gosh. Yeah. Yeah, I had that moment a
few months ago as a mathematician, you
know, like I was like, I am better than
this AI in certain like pulling together
all the math concepts and it came up
with a theorem and I was like, oh crap,
I would never ever in a million years
have figured that one out and then it
started making no mistakes and I'm like,
okay, maybe I should delete
mathematician now, you know, like go
back to like G GPU acquirer. It's still
for me still not fully got there with
the kind of complex pattern spotting
that is markets and particularly macro
which is super complex.
It hasn't got there yet but it will do.
I mean it's pretty good but it can't
connect the dots of a conversation I'm
having with you and what it might mean
for an asset there and what it means for
this all of the stuff that we do in our
heads.
>> Yeah. I think that it's a function of
two things. One is math is a very
verifiable domain right versus
open-ended. And two, it's because you've
only got like a dozen claude agents
working on it at once.
When you've got a hundred or a thousand
of them, they'll definitely be able to
figure out the angles. One funny thing,
like a couple of
>> I'm going to hit you up about that
because I'm building a a sort of
prediction model, you using universal
code as its kind of first principles
approach. Um, it's been doing some
testing, but I think you're right. Well,
I'm going to pick your brain about it.
in Singapore. I think I could get a
bunch of agents to just keep using
probabilistic outcomes. What fails, what
doesn't fail, get it to self-learn is a
better way of doing it than me [ __ ]
around with every day.
>> Yeah, pretty much. This is how you do
the hill climbing on the auto research,
right? That's why we optimize the auto
research function. So, it has this
recursive loop and it has an adaptive
loop as well. And sometimes even when
you kick it through different
modalities, it understands stuff like
you know when it doesn't quite hit a
like a report the angles that you want.
Yeah,
>> you can actually ask it to shape rotate
the argument after visualizing it and it
actually works. So give that a try for
some of those frustrating things where
it isn't quite fitting in place yet
>> because it activates a different part of
the latent space.
>> Um it works particularly well if you
tell it to visualize it and then shape
rotate it until it clicks into place.
Like again there's so much of these
models that we haven't done
>> because that's how that's how my brain
works because I'm so visual. That's how
I see it that everything is like a
connected network and I try and explain
it to my claude to do that
>> and you're rotating it in your brain but
you don't think to tell that to your
claude. You literally tell it visualize
what we've done all the arguments with
as many different angles as possible in
whatever output format you want. Then I
want you to shape rotate this so it
clicks into place across of these as
strongly as possible. Try it with
multiple agents and average the best
output. And it actually works because
that's how the latent space is. But you
wouldn't think it's that for some reason
because again we're still viewing it as
different but actually it is. This is
why I can understand games and entire
environments now. Why Fable is a step up
on multiffactor models and things like
markets and even writing, you know, like
it doesn't write like garbage. It
doesn't write great unless you figure
out things like this. We've
>> No, but it's it's getting better.
>> Yeah, it's getting better and you know
where it's going.
>> Yeah. Amazing. Emad, as ever, a
fantastic conversation and um I'll see
you in person soon and we'll get you
back on real vision soon.
>> Pleasure as always, sir.
>> All right, take care. This episode is
brought to you by Pith. Pith Network is
the fastest growing financial data
company today. Trusted by Fidelity
Investments, the US Department of
Commerce, Revolute, Kelshi, Jane Street,
Coinbase, and many more. They provide
real time financial market data across
over 3,000 equities, commodities,
crypto, FX, rates, and again, a lot
more. They're the first and largest
provider of 24/7 financial indices and
offer the widest array of market data
for the lowest cost. So go to
pith.network to take advantage of their
free trial. So, you obviously like this
video enough that you've got to the end.
That's quite a big task, but listen, do
me a favor. Hit the like and subscribe
button and also check out what video's
next because I think you'll love it. But
if you want even more, and when I'm
talking more, I'm talking about
memberergenerated ideas, incredible
alpha research, everything there to help
you in your journey, just head to
realton.com/join
for the best financial intelligence out
there and the pure alpha that's within
the platform.